Ever heard of good and bad cholesterol?
That's how I was initially taught about
the cholesterol containing particles in
our bloodstream. And that's probably how
it's still taught to patients and in
basic physiology courses. But it's a
lie.
Well, maybe I took that a bit too far.
It's not exactly a lie. Actually,
nothing of the sort. It does speak to
the evolution in science, especially as
it relates to good cholesterol, known as
HDL cholesterol. So, here's what I'd
like to do. I've pulled seven studies on
HDL, and I'd like to explain why the
doctors of the past may have been wrong
about HDL as it relates to heart health.
It's not all that good of a cholesterol
after all, and we have multiple lines of
evidence proving that to be true. Then
I'd like to explain why HDL cholesterol
may be the wrong focus and something
else might be on the horizon that may be
significantly better. First, we should
understand why scientists and doctors
even thought that HDL cholesterol was a
good cholesterol in the first place. I
mean, they did have their reasons. Back
in the 1970s and for several decades
later, it was believed that HDL
cholesterol or so-called good
cholesterol may be protective against
heart disease because it often tracked
with lower heart disease rates. Said
differently, the higher your blood HDL
cholesterol levels, the lower your risk
of having a heart attack. You might be
aware of the saying that correlation
beth not causation however or
correlation is not causation.
Essentially just because something
tracks with an outcome reduced heart
disease does not necessarily mean that
it caused this protection against heart
disease. One way to test if HDL
cholesterol causes heart disease
protection is to raise it independently
of anything else. So you know like 10 15
years ago or so pharmaceutical companies
and other institutions created drugs to
raise HDL cholesterol. In the end they
showed that HDLC did not cause a
protective effect against cardiovascular
disease like heart specific disease.
Even using natural substances like niain
which is vitamin B3 which is known to
raise HDL cholesterol had no effect as
seen here. The higher the lines go, the
more cardiovascular disease occurred.
Since both lines are similar, confirmed
statistically over four years of
treatment. The conclusion was that
nascin, at least in this formulation,
did not protect the heart, although it
raises HDL cholesterol. Now, I should
quickly mention because some people have
been following my work for a few years
now and may ask, there are trials that
show that nycin is effective against
cardiovascular disease, as I've covered
before, but the doses tend to be higher
and the formulation is different. So,
it's possible and even likely that we
can't blame HDL cholesterol for this
lack of effectiveness. And in fact,
there were other drugs that were tried,
but these drugs designed to raise this
good cholesterol actually showed harm
causing people to die more when they
were on them. So, is it the HDL or is it
the offtarget effects causing this lack
of an effect? Well, there's no doubt
that the molecule used to raise HDL
cholesterol makes a difference,
especially since some some of those
molecules have some additional effects,
if you know what I mean, muddying the
conclusions. However, better studies
with better interventions like this one,
where other blood fats like LDL
cholesterol are kept stable still show
no benefit of exclusively raising HDL
cholesterol. So, in combination across
multiple randomized control trials
designed to study this one issue, no
matter how you slice it, it looks like
actually raising HDL cholesterol has no
heart protection effect. Heck, we don't
even need to rely on clinical trials,
which of course have their
methodological issues like what we
touched on. We can turn to genetics. For
example, did you know that there are
people among us that have naturally high
HDL cholesterol levels? They're people
with a series of gene mutations that
will raise HDL. So, we can compare their
lifelong elevated HDL cholesterol to
people without these gene mutations.
People with normal HDL cholesterol. Now,
of course, a common question comes up.
Well, sure, their HDL cholesterol may be
high, but you know what else is
different? That's a good and fair
question if you were thinking it. The
way these studies are done, the
researchers focus on genes that only
raise HDL with no impact anywhere else.
Beyond that, these studies are a lot
like randomized control trials, but
better because people are randomly put
into a high HDL cholesterol group or a
control group at birth. And when we
group all the different groups of people
with these mutations compared against
those without, here we have 20 different
studies. This is a forest plot. So the
individual studies have their data shown
in the black squares. So if the squares
move to the left of the vertical middle
line, there's reduced risk of myioardial
inffection, which is a fancy way of
saying heart attack. But all the data
combined into one easyto read score is
at the very bottom as the diamond. No
matter how you slice it, if that's the
pool data or even as the most individual
studies, those with lifelong elevated
HDL cholesterol do not experience
protection from heart disease, at least
by this metric. And make no mistake,
other similar studies also show these
results to be true. All in all, now the
genetic studies confirm the clinical
data that HDL cholesterol does not
directly protect the heart. This is in
opposition of the epidemiological
evidence. So then is HDL cholesterol
useless then? Well, not quite. In fact,
it tells us several important things,
including something that scientists have
been relatively recently been
discovering. Before I get into all that,
you know that there have been these
banners on the screen. Those are to let
you know that if you want more
information on each section, like the
genetic studies or how two other blood
markers relate to cardiovascular disease
and even something called HDL
dysfunction and how it's getting more
and more attention and how to think
about this new HDL dysfunction evidence,
then check out the full version of this
video that you're watching. You'll get
an accompanying article including simple
summary and much more as a physionic
insider. The Physionic Insiders is my
research platform and comes with all
these perks like a private podcast, live
sessions, and much more. If you want a
deep dive analysis of your health
delivered to you every week, consider
joining. The link to join the Physionic
Insiders is in the description. I hope
to see you there. Okay, let's start
here. This is the relationship between
death and HDL cholesterol. And all you
need to know is if the lines go up, that
ain't good. Now, this shows an
association between low HDL here and
high HDL here being linked to increased
risk of death. So, what I'm trying to
say to you is if HDL cholesterol is very
low or if it's very high, there may be a
warning sign there. Something may be
wrong. Consider it like a a yellow flag.
not necessarily positive of harm, but it
should raise questions as to why the
values are so low or so high. Usually
that's reflected in other health poor
health metrics as well. Now, the other
thing that it might tell us about is
potential HDL dysfunction. Now, for us
to get into this last part, I'm going to
take a step back and uh because I've
been making some assumptions up to now,
like you knowing the difference between
HDL and HDL cholesterol, which are
actually two different things. If you're
looking at me with a face of like
confusion like this, then you're who I'm
talking to. Unless that's always your
face, in which case it's a tossup. HDL
stands uh for highdensity lipoprotein
and it's a particle that contains
cholesterol. Easy peasy. So when we're
talking about HDL cholesterol, we're
talking about the measure of the
cholesterol molecules found inside the
HDL particle. They're related, but HDL
cholesterol measures don't fully inform
on the number or function of the HDL
particles themselves. So, I'm bringing
this up because while we've seen some
considerable evidence that raising HDL
cholesterol does not protect against
heart disease directly, we do not know
if raising the particle number, the
number of vessels or the quality of
those particles could be directly
helpful. The actual particle can become
dysfunctional, meaning that it doesn't
work as effectively as it should. That
also means that people with exceedingly
low or exceedingly high LDL cholesterol
may also suffer from HDL dysfunction.
This is an area that's currently being
investigated. I know I've been talking a
while, but here's how I would approach
this all based on the evidence. So, I
would pay loose attention to my HDL
cholesterol numbers. If they are within
range, not too low, not too high. I
wouldn't think about it more than that
and move on to other health markers like
uh I don't know fasting blood glucose,
LDL, APOB and so on. If my values were
very low or very high, I would not focus
on trying to raise or lower them
exclusively. I'd probably look at other
tests like triglycerides, my fat mass,
and other areas that of my health that
affect my total health rather than
focusing on the HDL cholesterol number
itself, even if it's giving me a
potential warning. The reality is your
HDL cholesterol is more so a marker than
something to directly target. I think
calling it a good cholesterol isn't
necessarily wrong considering that it
doesn't directly contribute to risk, but
it's more so a neutral cholesterol than
anything. Now, you want to know another
area that doctors had to rethink? Well,
blood pressure and heart disease. I
discuss it in depth right here. Thanks
for tuning in. I hope this was helpful
and I'll speak with you in the next one.
Bye.